You've learned
about how RNNs work
and how they can be applied
to problems like name
entity recognition
as well as to language modeling.
You saw how back propagation
can be used to train an RNN.
It turns out that one
of the problems of
the basic RNN algorithm
is that it runs
into vanishing
gradient problems.
Let's discuss that and in the
next few videos we'll talk
about some solutions that
will help to address
this problem.
You've seen pictures of
RNNs that look like this.
Let's take a language
modeling example.
Let's say you see this sentence.
The cat, which already
ate and maybe already
ate a bunch of food
that was delicious,
dot dot, dot, dot, dot was full.
To be consistent is because
the cat is singular,
it should be the cat was
where there was the cats,
which already ate a bunch
of food was delicious
and the apples and
pears and so on were full.
To be consistent, it should
be cat was or cats were.
This is one example of
when language can have
very long-term
dependencies where it
worded as much earlier can
affect what needs to come
much later in the sentence.
But it turns out
that the basic RNN
we've seen so far is not
very good at capturing very
long-term dependencies.
To explain why, you might
remember from our earlier
discussions of training
very deep neural networks
that we talked about the
vanishing gradients problem.
This is a very, very
deep neural network,
say 100 years or
even much deeper.
Then you would carry out forward
prop from left to right
and then backprop.
We said that if this is a
very deep neural network,
then the gradient
from this output
y would have a very
hard time propagating
back to affect the weights
of these earlier layers,
to affect the computations
of the earlier layers.
For an RNN with a
similar problem,
you have forward prop going
from left to right and
then backprop going
from right to left.
It can be quite
difficult because of
the same vanishing gradients
problem for the outputs of
the errors associated with
the later timesteps to
affect the computations
that are earlier.
In practice, what this means
is it might be difficult to get
a neural network to realize
that it needs to memorize.
Did you see a singular noun or
a plural noun so that later
on in the sequence it can
generate either was or were,
depending on whether it
was singular or plural.
Notice that in
English this stuff in
the middle could be
arbitrarily long.
You might need to memorize
the singular plural for
a very long time before you get
to use that bit of information.
Because of this problem,
the basic RNN model has
many local influences,
meaning that the output y hat
three is mainly influenced by
values close to y hat three and
a value here is
mainly influenced
by inputs that are
somewhat close.
It's difficult for the
output here to be strongly
influenced by an input that
was very early in the sequence.
This is because
whatever the output is,
whether this got it
right, this got it wrong,
it's just very difficult
for the error to
backpropagate all the way
to the beginning
of the sequence,
and therefore to modify how
the neural network is doing
computations earlier
in the sequence.
This is a weakness of
the basic RNN algorithm,
one which will to address
in the next few videos.
But if we don't address it,
then RNNs tend not to be
very good at capturing
long-range dependencies.
Even though this
discussion has focused
on vanishing gradients,
you remember,
when we're talking about very
deep neural networks that
we also talked about
exploding gradients.
Where doing backprop,
the ingredients should not
just decrease
exponentially they may
also increase exponentially with
the number of layers
you go through.
It turns out that
vanishing gradients
tends to be the biggest
problem with training RNNs.
Although when
exploding gradients
happens it can be
catastrophic because
the exponentially
large gradients
can cause your
parameters to become
so large that your neural
network parameters
get really messed up.
It turns out that exploding
gradients are easier
to spot because the
parameter has just blow up.
You might often see
NaNs, not a numbers,
meaning results of a
numerical overflow
in your neural
network computation.
If you do see
exploding gradients,
one solution to that is
apply gradients clipping.
All that means is,
look at your gradient vectors,
and if it is bigger
than some threshold,
re-scale some of your
gradient vectors
so that it's not too big,
so that is clipped according
to some maximum value.
If you see exploding gradients,
if your derivatives do
explore the resilience,
just apply gradient clipping.
That's a relatively
robust solution
that will take care of
exploding gradients.
But vanishing gradients
is much harder to
solve and it will be the
subject of the next few videos.
To summarize, in
an earlier course,
you saw how we're training
a very deep neural network.
You can run into vanishing
gradient or exploding
gradient problems where the
derivative either
decreases exponentially,
or grows exponentially as
a function of the
number of layers.
An RNN, say an RNN
processing data over
1,000 times sets,
or over 10,000 times sets,
that's basically
a 1,000 layer or
like a 10,000 layer
neural network.
It too runs into these
types of problems.
Exploding gradients
you could solve
address by just using
gradient clipping,
but vanishing gradients will
take way more to address.
What we'll do in the next
video is talk about GRUs,
a greater recurrent units,
which is a very effective
solution for addressing
the vanishing gradient
problem and will allow
your neural network to capture
much longer range dependencies.
Let's go on to the next video.